all right hello everyone it's November
3rd
2024 I'm going to begin active infer an
stream number 6.1 as per usual with a
GitHub push and then let's jump right
into the repo and this should be an
awesome stream so thanks to those who
are joining live for those who are
interested in Biore Regional modeling
open source active inference toolkits
and more this should be quite exciting
so I'm excited to walk through where
things have gotten over the last few
days and talk about how we'll continue
over the next 10 days Plus+ plus all of
this is happening in the open source
repo iio firm a to John Clipper's idea
I'm sure we'll return to this in a lot
of different ways in the coming stream
and everything that I'm about to go
through is the current state on biofirm
we just push the update let's reload to
confirm
awesome welcome John all right there's
two aspects of the biofirm concept that
the current state of the repo and this
stream are going to demonstrate the
first is the active inference component
which is an active inference-based
multi-agent control framework One agent
deployed per ecological modality with
differing levels of noise and
controlability within a general
homeostatic framework all of this of
course work in program add simple where
possible however I ran into a lot of fun
ways to work with pmdp over the last few
days using cursor
0.42 the second part of the biofirm
research is going to reuse some code
from gen 24 this is going to use
perplexity llm with internet access
calls with an API to do some Biore
Regional research and structuring and
reporting for California
counties okay where are we going and
then let's jump first into the active
inference component
stream okay the goals of the stream are
to First demonstrate a proof of concept
for Biore Regional modeling using active
inference Frameworks building on what
Andrew P and others have done second to
prepare
work towards preparing some open source
Biore Regional templating for the coming
applied active inference
Symposium and then third explore pmdp
methods and simulations and get a better
sense for what's really happening with
that ABCD after
all okay detailed agenda just to read
the highlights then we'll jump into one
one bio Regional modeling outputs and
impact two more foundational background
three we'll go into detail on pmdp
partially observable marov decision
process
PDP four talk a little bit more about
bioriginal modeling and then there's a
bunch of discussion
topics all right here's where we're
going with this simulation so I'll walk
through the visualizations
first here is 10 ecological
variables this uses in the utils file
I'm going to jump around a little bit so
ask any questions in the chat and also
look at it synchronously on your own
time ecosystem config.js is going to
describe the variables as well as their
relationships amongst them I kept that
part empty but it does work each
variable has an initial value which is
set at 50 and a constraint homeostatic
range here for all the variables it's
set up 45 to
55 then
each variable has several important
factors that determine its
controlability first is a trend
coefficient this does work however I've
left them as zero for now and then two
main factors that we're going to be
exploring a lot which is the control
strength and the noise standard
deviation so what's going to happen in
ecosystem simulation is it is going to
run a random setting and watch the
ecosystem unroll with no control and
then it's also going to run an active
inference simulation where depending on
the control ability the active inference
agent is able to re-enter those scaled
controls back into the ecosystem so to
get started first you run from the
scripts folder for now Python 3 and then
startup. py startup. py is going to
install into a python virtual
environment
the pmdp package and then you need to
run Source VM bin activate in order to
get it going you'll know that you're in
it because it'll say VM and it won't be
like where's pmdp I already downloaded
that it's in VM here so we can skip the
Python 3 startup the big script to run
is ecosystem simulation so here's what
happens when it
runs first it brings in a bunch of
dependencies let's run it so that we see
what it looks like first and then we'll
walk through the
logic it logs
variables this is a deep debugging error
so that's not done yet it does the
active
inference simulation does the random
simulation then the active inference
simulation saves all the logging into
the output
folder it's going to talk about
generating these visual ation and then
we're going to go to the visualizations
folder and we're going to look at
those so in this case while it's logging
we'll start to look
through it's going to be doing 1,000
time steps so it'll run the same random
seed for random uncontrolled setting and
for active inference partial control
setting for a thousand time steps
discrete time discret State space and
print an extended log to the terminal
every 100 time steps it's going to
inject to control action every time step
that could be changed and have some
logging information which was really a
lot of the fun
okay here's some dictionary methods
here's the primary
environment possibly in the future could
be improved just like everything else so
many different ways RX iner RX
environments Etc but this is just an
environment
class loading and validating the configs
reads in the number of eological variabl
so to change the number of ecological
variables this is a place where cursor
does amazing things so we're in the
ecosystem config and say write 10 more
ecologically relevant variables
for
California okay meanwhile we finished
the main visualizations from the
ecosystem simulation we're going to look
at them in a second and then now it's
going into this second level analysis
for just the free energy principle
active inference type analyses which
we'll look at second that's not totally
working I still just wanted to do this
now it gives enough of a
Direction but just to pull back to
cursor and how we can use the semantics
of natural language to modify structured
data so here's that ecosystem
config and then it's added a bunch of
more ecological modalities and then if
we were to run
ecosystem simulation again it would use
those new modalities and make an even
longer plot so I'm just going to reject
that but that's how that works
okay so again it loads in the config
including the variable relationships
which are not utilized here checks for
circular dependencies some of this is
just to make a script-like flow of
course in RX and fur and so on there's
more advanced ways to deal with this
type of graph iCal
specification running
simulation it runs it with an active
inference agent if needed you can also
call it in random only
mode what it's going to do is for each
of the controllable modalities in the
ecosystem config
file
so each of these modalities controllable
is true if it's controllable equals
false it's something that's not going to
be analyzed as controllable then that
doesn't need to spin up uh control
active agent maybe there could be a
sense making agent that gets spun up but
it's it's uh just everything being
modeled as controllable to different
extents
here it runs the simulation we're going
to look more into the logic of the
biofirm agent and also the the PDP ABCD
matrices it runs a
simulation what happens at each time
step of the simulation is that there's
the natural underlying dynamics of the
natural resource or proxy on the 0 to
100 scale continuous value then at each
time step that gets distilled to a z one
or two just three discrete values either
low within homeostasis or high there's
three options and that simplifies the
input space for the otim agent we'll
talk more about this when we get to the
generative model
then the D agent per that bi that biom
modality does hidden State inference
then policy inference samples an action
and then returns that action as either a
negative one which is
decrease so here it is with the
observation being converted to 01 or two
then the active agent is going to do
inference on sense making an action
selection returning negative 1 decrease
zero maintain or plus one increase that
control signal is going to get Scaled by
the controllability of the ecological
Factor so there's the natural noise
variation happening every time step and
then also if it's controllable with
active inference in that case it
re-inject the control signal multiplied
by the controlability
here's the step function also just to
note that the Claude 3.5 Sonet 2024 1022
that came out 10 or so days ago it's
markedly better with cursor 42 than fire
these scripts are getting to around 1 to
2,000 lines each which is incredible
because from even prior active infan
streams you'll remember where we were
breaking things up after about 2 or
300 performance metrics are
logged various logging it's hard to know
if you're going too too hard or not hard
enough on logging tracking is initiated
states are recorded
just getting through all of this here's
the initialization of the active
inference agent we'll talk about how
that's specified when we get to its
logic after looking at the outputs and
then that's the main script okay so
here's what those visualizations get you
and how this this is just schematic it's
not meant to actually be like here's the
kind of situations where it works or not
it's just comparing it against a simple
maintain random noise strategy we can
add other strategies and other
algorithms for policy selection to
compare better okay control actions
analysis this plots red random for green
active inference and it plots the the
occupancy also each of the ecological
variables of course they're just meant
to be schematic they're appended with
the noise and the
controllability so you can start to
explore and we'll talk more about that
in the parameter sweep what is the
controllability of different noise
variables and controllability
intensities so looking at soil PH which
has a every time step a noise
variability of 07 standard deviation
sampling from normal there and then a
controllability of 2.8 which means that
every time the negative one is output
decrease it goes down by 2.8 points
overall so this is quite controllable
and we see it spending a lot more of its
time near the homeostatic
range because it's able ble to control
an amount that is slightly larger than
the noise
Factor here's another situation with the
nutrient levels where we see control 1.8
versus
noise6 and so it's able to navigate
towards these homeostatic bands so this
is the occupancy with the control
actions across
these soil compaction this is another
interesting one even with a smaller
control it's able to stay Within in the
space because also as with all Gan noise
processes the expected value going
through time of random noise is the same
value as the starting value it's just
that the variance is higher okay
correlation heat Maps here's looking at
the correlations amongst these variables
in the random case on the left and the
active inference case on the right and
we can look at certain things like soil
structure and see that okay it's lighter
here it's darker here so this is just to
show you can look at the correlation
structure of the Dynamics of different
variables and whatever it is that the
actim policy is doing it is changing the
correlation structure so it's not just
recapitulating
random satisfaction rates so
satisfaction rates are the percentage of
time that that that across all variables
each variable spends in the homeostatic
zone so it starts out High because the
initial value starts at 100 for all of
or starts at 50 which is right in the
middle of their zone for all of them and
then random control diffuses out and we
can run a longer time step simulation
soon let's actually just run it in the
background to show how that works and
then it will like reset so I'm going to
go
to the ecosystem
simulation change the number of time
steps to
10,000 save it clear it run the
simulation first it's going to this is
the random so that's
faster and and at each of those 100
loged time it's basically oscillating
like 0 to 20% and there's no control
effort because it's not selecting policy
and then it's giving a play byplay and
then you'll see on the bottom that it
will
um switch to different logging mode once
the actm comes into play okay continuing
on through here so we looked at
satisfaction rate here's another way to
look at State distributions so this is
the top is the random control bottom is
the active inference so we can see okay
well um in the random setting again
these are just schematic there's not any
ecological validity uh soil structure
spent about half the time in low and
half in high and over here it spent more
time in high and homeostatic um State
transitions this is looking at the the
history of policy
selection in terms of how did the
transitions amongst the different states
go so in the soil organic matter low
always went to low almost always 0. N9
and little time was spent in high at all
whereas those numbers are different
there just one visualization that can
happen here's the new visualizations and
they'll overwrite these okay this is a
great way to look at the difference
between these two remember from the same
random seed and the same underlying
randomization Dynamics is
happening for both active inference and
for the random case okay it's kind of a
large image it's easier to see some of
these things when you only have like one
or three modalities so
let's
okay here we
go so this is strategy comparison actm
is on the right Natural Evolution of
that uncontrolled Dynamics are on the
left
so here we can
see they're they're varying in the
amount of controllability and
noise but we can look at how they move
with in and out of that
band system stability analysis this is
another fun one this is just three
random variables chosen but we can see
from this phase space Excursion plot is
it popping up at you is it pushing back
away from you we can see that the otim
diffusion is
constrained because there's this partial
homeostatic control and there's
different control theoretic metric we
can
make average control effort I think this
we can look at how it's calculated but
it just relates to how much change is
happening step by step and the variable
distributions again this is looking
at gray
random blue OCT active inference
agent so here again we have that soil PH
the blue line for active inference
spending much more of its time in the
homeostatic range while the gray random
policy maintain plus random noise has a
more diffuse shape so sometimes it's
it's bodal sometime and and in the large
limit you can with many more time steps
I've run several for like 50 or 100,000
and those have more of a convergence
property so these are the kinds of
things that we can study like in the
coming 10 10 days and Beyond let's look
at the satisfaction rate so here it only
did slightly better so again it's it's
it's not intended to say that active
inference does literally any better than
random in any given case it doesn't
necessarily do that it may not do better
or simpler than any other kind of policy
selection at all it's just about
bringing this onto the table and looking
at how pmdp facilitates that and then
last piece of the outputs each of the
outputs has a modality specific folder
and these have several visualizations
some of them are going to glitch but it
looks like this is a belief distribution
earlier versions ancient amandus like
earlier versions of the script had a lot
more informative super cool looking
things happening here but this is just
for now it's it's the the margin doesn't
allow what needs to be shown in these
dashboards but there's a lot of methods
and uh partially partially broken SLP
partially functional code and that's
what's happening now so when you run the
ecosystem main simulator it'll run the
number of time steps for random for
active inference it will do those
overall highlevel visualizations that we
just looked at in that folder and then
in the active inference analysis it
looks more like the expected free energy
belief Dynamics a bunch of other stuff
okay so we saw just from looking at that
that there were certain combinations
that seemed to do well and then there
was certain combinations where the
control was not working very well so
here again in an amazing example of how
knowing that a certain kind of analysis
would be preferable having seen it in
other papers just thinking about it
yourself and so on here is going to be a
sweep
run across control abilities
so here it's
multi-threaded we can use this we can
this is super fun I was going pretty
high given everything they have on these
older
computers here we have number of CPUs
this is going to be separate replicate
virtual threads or physical threads if
you have them for running this sweep
noise range and control range are going
to be the log
space variability so here we let's go
from 0.1 to
one and so that that'll
be sampling from from a tenth to to one
let's do it to two just like a had and
we'll do 10 points along each so this is
going to do 100 simulations across all
combinations of noise and
controllability here we'll do 200 otim
time steps and then this is fun number
of repeats so here we can run five
replicates at the exact same setup to
get conversion properties and
stationarity at the within experimental
replicate like within quote biological
replicate but this is like doing
technical replication so again all this
is going to be useful as we continue to
develop this analysis let's just do it
with these numbers 200 may not be enough
to show differences let's just but it's
going to take 3 * 200 for each of a 100
but it's going to divide that by eight
because it's going to have eight threads
on this computer so Python 3 noise
control
okay okay great that's not taking too
long and we haven't yet looked at what
is the bioferm agent itself these are
just the outputs of it and the sweeping
of it after showing this sweep analysis
I'm going to pull back to the biofirm
agent and how the ABCD matrices are
scaled okay so here we have in
outputs sweep
this was a must have been an earlier
slightly earlier
analysis
so let's look at this while it's
running belief entropy service doesn't
look to be calculated properly but
that's kind of
cool control effort surface again not
necessarily calculated but
fun satisfaction rate surface
whoa so here we
have as you have lower
variability you and it's a short
simulation so with low variability like
0.001 even with 100 or 300 in a row it
doesn't escape the very the satisfaction
range of plus or minus 5 whereas we see
as we go down towards higher noise we
end up spending more time outside of the
h static
bound interaction again this is all just
just meant to be speculative realism
coding different control
efforts here we see satisfaction
rates and see okay it looks like you
have more
control this bottom row when the noise
is in that quintile then this is a more
control efficacy we can see satisfaction
rate dropping as variability is
higher here's a heat
map satisfaction rate so that's in
yellow down to Blue is a satisfaction
rate noise SD on the left control
strength on the
right so these are probably not sampled
from stationarity because it was only a
few hundred times but I did some runs
for a few hours
where you can run 10 replicates per cell
so it gives you a strong differentiating
signal at each cell and then run each of
those replicates technical replicates
for like
10,000 so that it comes to a
stationerity or use a burn burn in
Period and then that starts to reveal
some really interesting
patterns Okay so
there's other parameters of sweep over I
mean I'm sure it's going to be a theme
we return to again and again and again
and again which is that while the ACM
models can be incredibly interpretable
simple effective etc etc often to
understand what is really being needed
are we trying to do sense making on
whether we're out of homeostasis or not
because otherwise we could say
observation confidence is 100 we just we
know 100% whether we're within or low or
high
or do we only want to have 55%
confidence in the signal coming from the
low homeostatic high but then to the
extent that actually that signal is
valid that's diluting the efficacy of
the control or we may set a very high
value for homeostasis to see more of a
pullback attractor effect but again if
it was as simple as saying low means
turn on the heater and high means turn
on the cooler if it was as simple as
that kind of a rule-based system you
wouldn't need to do expected free energy
pragmatic Value Plus epic epistemic
value at all so we're going to return to
this okay now let's get to what is the
biofirm
agent all
right the the biofirm agent and again
this is drawing on clippinger work and
also Andrew P's work and how he set this
up it's an active inference agent bundle
for ecosystem control creates n
independent PDP partially observable
markof decision process agents one per
controllable modality each PDP agent
takes in a discrete observation low
homeostatic or high and this is kind of
fun as we talk towards what could be a
generalized active agent or kind of a
minimal essential kernel and all that by
saying well we're going to let the
simulation map the generative process
the environment map from whatever the
value is
actually out there like in degrees to
just this homeostatic variable or I
thought well we could have more Nuance
we could have a five State model like
too low getting low just right little
bit warm too warm and then that'd be a
5x5 but here it's a three State
observation then there's three hidden
States as well are we actually low
homeostatic or high that's mapped by the
a matrix the B Matrix
goes from to Hidden State
transitions with each slice being in
affordance one action policy which is
either decrease maintain do nothing or
stay C is the same shape and size as a
distribution over observations and then
D is just to get the chain rolling the
initial hidden State prior which is just
uniform so what's going to happen using
pmdp is first an observation is going to
come in from the ecosystem simulation
that's going to be a one hot just a one0
0 if it's low or 0 1 0 if it's in
homeostatic or 001 if it's high and so
on that is going to get pushed through
the a matrix the 3X3 to end up with a
belief distribution over lat and States
like is it really cold or homeostatic or
hot given the observation that's the
initial variational free energy sense
making then expected free energy is used
for policy selection which is given my
updated beliefs about lat and state
distributions what would be the play out
for each of these slices of B evaluated
in terms of epistemic and pragmatic
value so here's what's going to happen
the biofirm rapper starts by
initializing the number of PDP agents
that it needs which is the number of
controllable variables that are in the
situation there's two free variables and
again this just depends how generalized
you want do you just want to say it's
0.9 and 0.1 confidence and we'll leave
it at that or do you want to do
parameter fitting on even higher order
variables learning and so on observation
confidence is going to be the on
diagonal element of a we'll look at that
in the pmdp homeostatic preference is
going to be the on homeostasis
preference enrichment in C and we'll
look at that too this was the main road
blocking and speed bumping and gapping
and lading was in andout of numpy arrays
list object all these different python
shapes and it's going to be awesome
already cursor demonstrably can make
some of this happen and building up
really
explicit really good
documentation then even if it's
online you can bring in the
pmdp documentation online
so this is super interesting it allows
us to say things in different places and
have that influence the model like if
it's like yeah it should be a numpy
right here and here's the method you use
somewhere else here's an example of
where it works use this code it works
then that will have really cascading
effects the ABCD matrices are made we're
going to look at those after walking
through the logic of the bioform agent
but each controllable modality has its
own agent so it isn't used using cross
Laten State information each of these is
meant to be a standalone
controller here we make each of those
modalities have their own
ABCD and check check check check check
all these different features there might
be some place where I'm doing it
redundantly right now moving it in and
out of a different format and I look
forward to irony those things out but it
works now
get
action is going to take in the
action that's selected which is again
like so many of these other small things
the actions like the affordances are
listed in terms of a zero index list
affordance 0 1 or two whereas we want it
to be into a control signal like
negative 1 0 or 1 kind of reverse
neutral or forward then here's the
scaling by control strength
so here in ecosystem config we can see
okay the controlability of microbial
activity is 1.2 so that means a positive
signal for there is going to result in
1.2 efficacy on the next time
step getting agent data this is about
logging information from the agent so
it's actually pretty simple what's
happening however there's a lot that's
happening underneath
the hood with a few different things
first the matrices being created and
this script we're going to look at in a
second and then also the pmdp methods
which is brought in the script clone
pmdp clones the whole repo which is
useful again for cursor to bring into
the context so it has all these positive
examples so for open source INF for ants
adding well documented effective code of
any kind probably is having big impact s
in how these language models through
their training and context are able to
make active inference models for dream
like scenarios
so that's what was used during the
creation of this package I just didn't
clone it onto this other computer um
agent. infer States is the perceptual
inference
component and then sample
action uh is also
used it might be missing one line here
or I can explore where else if it's
doing the where it's doing the expected
free energy based methods I tried
several different ways for doing that
efe step ranging
[Music]
from um using the PDP methods to
calculating the epistemic value and the
pragmatic value separately again this is
just intended to be a sort of a scaffold
and I look forward to to ironing out a
few of the low hanging fruit in the
coming days here's the PVP matrices that
are invoked for each of the modality
specific agents by the
biofirm observation confidence again is
going to be the on diagonal a matrix
homeostatic preference is going to be
the middle homeostatic preference in the
C PDP matrices is a method that wraps
around specifying ABCD parameterized
using the config parameters checks the
shape moves them in and out of a bunch
of different
things here's the initialization of a so
this creates a simple 3x3 likelihood
Matrix mapping observations empirical
observations to latent States so from a
one hot observation to a belief over
hidden
States if you have confidence equals 1
100% confidence then it's just an
identity Matrix and the one hot
observation maps to a one hot belief of
lated States if you had noise being
lower uh I'm sorry confidence being
higher so that noise was a nonzero value
then a has an off diagonal component so
what happens is first the diagonals are
filled with a confidence then the off
diagonals are filled with these kinds of
confusions and then
the other half of the noise per column
is added to the the mega confusions
which would be the probability of
thinking that it's hot given that the
observation came in cold so here's what
it kind of ends up looking like at the
end we have from and two and the bigger
numbers are on the identity axis and
then we have these noise over two
remainder from one on these off
dials another place where better usage
of PMP methods and more examples could
help is in the normalizing of different
A and B matrices here's where we get to
the B
Matrix B Matrix is regarding latent
States you can look at textbook
group figure 4.3 or 7.3 as we often do B
is going to intervene in how hidden
States change Through Time B is a tensor
each slice of B is from and to
lat and
States as a matrix and then each slice
like an index card is which affordance
is being selected so here's the B Matrix
policy selection is selecting out a
slice of the index card of B and then
that is used as a transition operator on
hidden
States so this is broken out and and
again there could be a lot of
interesting ways to improve how this is
written but here are the three actions
decrease maintain and increase and again
this is where it comes to a learning PDP
experience and for future software
packages where each of these values have
a real interpretability and here there's
no learning or updating so this speaks
to part of the interpretability of how
policies are determined in active
inference is we can say this is the
fixed beliefs or these are the updatable
beliefs and how they're updatable about
the effects of policy so it's not just
training the weights continuous values
for n billion nodes it's doing Matrix
operations with these investigable
matrices so here this is the situation
where we take a decrease action so this
is kind of like turning on the the air
conditioning for a
room this is from and to so this is the
the probability of staying in
low given that you're in low and you
chose decrease 90% of the time you stay
in low 10% of the time you go to
homeostatic 0% of the time you go to
High let's just look at another one
given that we chose maintain and we
started in
homeostasis our belief is that 80% of
the time we transition to stay in
homeostasis and 10% of the time we go to
either hot or cold and again one more
for increasing it's the mirror here
doesn't have to be but it is
for decrease and low I'm saying given
that we chose increase this slice of
B and that we were in high we're going
to stay in high with a 90% probability
10% going to homeostasis so again this
was a big thing in the in the fitting
was this is a relatively sharp belief
about the efficacy of policy I mean
thinking that it we have too few soil
microbes we took this one policy and
then does it have a 90% probability of
moving us to homeostasis at the next
time step probably not so how do you
deal with multiscale policy nesting
different efficacies learning on b
parameterizing b based upon causal
relationships and other structures this
is um just intended as a scheme that's B
so we looked at a sensemaking matrix B
conditional action transition operations
now C so C is
three elements in a list
array the low and high are given a value
of one 0.1 kind of arbitrarily and then
homeostatic preference is the middle
value so if the the value was four it'd
be
0.14.1 and that's reflecting the
preference that's going to get
normalized for the
homeostatic middle value so that's C and
then D is only used one time at the
beginning of the simulation
it's intended to just be basically
uniform but giving a tiny Edge to
homeostasis just to make the numbers add
up it's a belief over hidden state so
for the very first time step it it
doesn't have a strong perspective on the
hidden state that it's in just waits for
the first
observation here validate matrices
validates as happens kind of internally
but it gives another level of
checking so what happens with biofirm
agent again pull all the way back to
ecosystem simulation this is going to
run the number of time steps for the
random case with just the uncontrolled
natural process then it's going to run
it again with the same random seed each
time step sending that low homeostatic
or high control signal to the biofirm
agent the biofirm agent has been set up
to process that kind of signal through
the ABCD matrices
a sense making B State transition
operation C preference taken into
account for expected free energy and
then D
prior
okay looking at a another way to talk
about this generative model and that's
what active inference modeling is
specifying the generative model running
it out having all these things where
even though the kernel of the simulation
is just like
delivering that latent State belief to
the expected free energy engine
iterating over policies updating the
policy prior into the policy posterior
selecting an action passing that back
that core extremely interpretable kernel
or nucleus has to have all of this kind
of logging and because there's so many
ways that that can happen it's not
enough just to say well just do this
particle collision and then let's take
the outcomes
okay so again just to restate um this is
in the generative model markdown on the
repo the simulation instantiates the
number of controllable modalities of
active inference agents that are bundled
under this
biofirm the parameters from the config
file are
used the PDP agent has these features of
taking in one of three different
discrete observations
here's for those who are learning and
studying and teaching pmdp more
information on a b c and needs a d
Matrix first there's the perceptual
State inference observation o subt comes
in variational free energy is used to
update
beliefs policy selection each policy Pi
computes expected free energy that can
be broken down as risk minus amb
ambiguity it can be broken down as
epistemic Value Plus pragmatic value but
again leading to this interesting
question when are we looking to have
pragmatic value from an ecosystem over
some time scale what about epistemic
action the control signal is output and
then scaled by the control strength and
then that re-enters the
simulation
okay so again just to close out this
first part it's in the scripts right now
it'll probably change over the coming 10
days or so to be a little bit more
reliable but ecosystem simulation calls
random simulation it calls biofirm agent
which loads in its matrices from the
ABCD script free energy minimization
provides visualization methods kind of
ideas
and salvageable materials for it and
then all of that gets output to Output
so this sets up a very
interesting possibility
for Biore Regional modeling and
connecting with digital Gaia all this
other exciting work happening in
regenerative agriculture financing all
these different kinds of areas that we
can start to hook together okay just to
briefly review a few more as we
transition more to the broader biofirm
concept okay
so
farmworks was a grant that emerged out
of the RX andur learning group at The
Institute with Vladimir bowan and his
colleagues and some others who joined in
where we
proposed developing an RX and fur based
system as an alternative implementation
to pmdp but ultimately as per
generalized notation notation work from
yakup and I in
2023 models can be specified in
generalized notation notation which is
open source by the way and then
implemented in different languages we
were getting really good results even in
2023 I think there' be super exciting
ways to revisit this for anyone who's
interested where we can distill out the
GNN so just for an example I'm going to
copy this figure 4.3 figure 7.3 type
model from step by
step make a new file GNN do
markdown paste it in it's a markdown
file that has the state
spaces so if we can connect this kind of
GNN representation to PDP ABCD GNN then
we're in a situation where we do our
engineering at the higher semantic level
and this is going to facilitate
interactive interfaces vastly instead of
needing to do all this Matrix operations
we'll just develop okay here's how you
go from this a matrix spec to a rendered
and normalized and validated a and so on
for ABCD and so on so little bit of a
GNN interlude but it's super exciting so
I would love to work on it with anyone
who wants to revisit it um in farmworks
building on Vladimir at all's vinq
decentralized AI system and with with
all these great participants we talk
about making a multi-agent RX infer very
biofirm like but with a focus on
Federated sovereignty in place-based
community and mitigating the effects of
the centralized AI so that's one place
to look for a little background firworks
development even though as of right now
we can update that to November 2024
still pending we're still developing on
on this I've done some Explorations with
Farm OS with the digital Gaia Gaia OS
methods with other methods so we're
still working on this
regardlessly just a little background
and then another place to look and learn
more and I eagerly await more
Publications and everything that'll
happen in the coming weeks from John
clippinger and the biofirm concept so
that pulls back to what is really a
biofirm and and of course it's still
being explored and all of that but I'm
going to use that openness as well as
and here's also a following up with
again Vladimir jono Andre Pasa others
driving really cool development on
connecting with the data sets that
already exist for vinq using farms and
others so not for today but for anybody
with with whatever your background or
interest is there are super exciting
ways to find epistemic and pragmatic
value in pursuing active inference
generative models for regenerative
agricultural Futures and Beyond just
wanted to make sure those who feel like
I don't know if this is the right place
for me to contribute or participate or
I've never done open source or I'm not
an academic or I'm not a farmer whatever
it is it's all good join the fun email
blanket active inference Institute if
you want that's a great Inlet or leave a
comment join our Discord all these kinds
of things check out where the Institute
is at because this is a fast moving
though very inclusive project so in the
openness around what is a biofirm I
started doing a little bit of research
into the dpsir model this is going to be
a short interlude that's going to take
us to the bio perplexity part and dpsir
stands for drivers's pressures State
impact and response models of
interventions so I'm thinking how can we
connect the on nft ontologies narrative
formal tools and documents of Biore
regionalism and regenerative agriculture
and all of this how can we connect that
to what is already in place and so
here's some ways to
map SP p d i and r to the bio firm
agents
itself just one super preliminary look
but how do we adapt that to the 100,000
last miles which our world is
constituted by and that gets to the
second part of this script package which
is the biop perplexity so now I'm going
to turn to using perplexity AI API for
doing research on bio regions so this is
an adaptation of the Gen AI system
prompts are different personas these
could be understood as like different
characters or skill sets or agents
within a biofirm we have ecological
researcher Market analyst supply chain
strategist Regulatory Compliance expert
and the biofirm business case manager
who's going to come in at the end sweep
it
up biofirm regions here I used an online
search and found what are all the 58
regions of California and then I said
make a Json format paste it in said for
all the regions of California Pace them
with a country and the state so of
course this can be generalized for other
countries other states within the United
States of America I just wanted to start
with a sort of fractal around where I am
which is in the penultimate County ID
number 56 in the Central Valley Yolo
County three steps are going to happen
for this a first step well here's first
just where we're going let's look at
Yolo County so this is research done for
each of the counties
each of the biofirm agents are going to
do online research using perplexity API
about the region so here's we'll look at
it in the markdown because it looks
nicer so here is the regular Regulatory
Compliance research
report here's the supply chain
strategist Yolo County research report
The Prompt can be tuned however from a
first look it it it really does okay
here it mentions UC Davis agricultural
sector UC Davis so it is actually doing
an online
search um what's going to happen in the
logic of the scripts first uh the API
key is in this get ignore file llm
Keys um it loads in the list of counties
that are in the
regions and Persona that are in the
system
prompts sends the
Persona and the prompt to
perplexity pulls
back the response saves it as adjacent
and then here is the research bio region
so it's saying do for those four first
four experts in index 0 1 2 3 4 do the
perplexity call with these four personas
then that gets concatenated into a
unified
markdown so here is the unified markdown
Consolidated research
markdown so it's just all of the reports
again they they could be improved it's
just the first pass that's the first
script research bio regions it iterates
over all of the regions here and then it
does the research
then here's biofirm business
pitch so this one is only going to use
the biofirm case
manager and so the case manager is a
expert business strategist who deals in
natural capital and biotechnology
Ventures I'm I'm not saying this is what
a biofirm or any of that is it just it's
a fun
possibility and what the second script
does is it takes in the Consolidated
research
report and then it generates a business
case for that report you could also
imagine this going to structured outputs
like how many hect acres of water are on
the surface or how many on a scale of 1
to 100 how many insects are there or how
many Studies have looked at microbial
diversity in that area and then that
could be given a structured number and
then input into the kinds of AC
inference models that we looked at in
the first half so let's look at the YOLO
business case Okay so any any Central
Valley funders see what you
think establish a biofirm natural
Capital company in Yolo County
California presents a compelling
opportunity due to the Region's Rich
biodiversity strong agricultural sector
and robust research
infrastructure unique opportunities
biodiversity hotspot research
infrastructure agricultural Innovation
conservation and restoration
competitive advantages Market
positioning this this could be done with
a catechism or any other kind of
business modeling structure business
model okay how are we going to do it how
is Davis cognitive security AKA whatever
the bio firm for Davis will be how will
it make money bioprospecting and product
development Precision
agriculture environmental biotechnology
Consulting and advisory
Services interest
let's look at Del Norte and see if a
different business case is
derived so here we in Del
Norte for reference this is the very
Northwest County of
California here the business model has
to do with bioproducts and
pharmaceuticals cool sustainable
forestry absent in Yolo and Marine
biotechnology also abs in Yolo County so
again just from
this sort of do four kinds of research
and save it into the four
specialist
files then concatenate together send all
that research along with the biofirm
closer the expert gets sent in gets
called again and then that outputs this
Consolidated business case we could use
structured API calls or just the
informal structuring again to extract
basian beliefs count how many biotech
companies are in each county in
California each County in the US or you
know each 50 mile hex radius in the
world and then take that into a
generative model that can be
specified so the third script we'll run
it Python
3 biofirm visualization
this one might take
longer so here we found 58 regions with
research data processing 290 documents
from 58 regions this is going to do a
linguistic semantic analysis on all the
documents that were in that folder so
visualizations folder is empty it's
going to take a few minutes for
processing this and then we'll look at
the visualizations and this is just
again preliminary
linguistic analysis we can start to
understand like well to what extent do
the word patterns used by the
Specialists differ to what extent do we
see region specific
language another interesting thing would
be in the in the regions we could put
the GPS coordinates or the north south
east west bounds and
then do like a regression analysis of
the the
geography aligned with the semantic
space embeddings and outputs and then we
can ask questions like are the semantic
spaces topological
relationships similar or different to
the
geography to what extent do we see north
south east
west to what extent do we see more
ecotone or E ecotype analysis okay we're
moving forward we've made four folders
comparative network analysis Regional
and topic
analysis okay just to read some
questions in the chat while this is
chugging John clippinger writes great
fabulous work for framing the problem
thank you John for all the work on
framing the problem Morgan wrote how
about for microbial ecology control are
there examples of that yeah great
question we could look it up and that is
sort of what we've been exploring in the
farmworks case vinq and FL and Vladimir
at all is how do we encode the efficacy
believed or and or empirically verified
of different treatments and also
highlight the conditionality of the
efficacy of the treatments like
treatment one works for disease 1 in
condition one but not two whereas
treatment two has a lower efficacy in
both cases but you can't put them both
and how do we take all of that
semi-structured information and bring it
into a generative model that we can
start to analyze and interpret okay
Regional
topics all right the again these are
just preliminary fun
visualizations so here we have topic
one trapping
in infill node industrialize interesting
this topic two is more of a generic
development sustainability here we see
again
trapping so there must be some anomalous
language use related to that cluster
okay or
not um Regional PCA oh wow oh
wow PCA component one look at this a
state divided shall not stand
PCA component
one Amador Yuba Del
Norte and then here we
have
other okay document
type okay it's clustering whether it's a
business case or a research report that
was the
split so here on the right we have all
of the PCA embeddings of the business
cases whereas on the left is all the
primary research Sano wordcloud that's
where I grew
up include development project Mato
County Environmental okay kind of
cool Regional term heat
map okay with this many variables it's
not necessarily informative but let's
look at this one
product we can see
some uh documents use the word product
or this one's the clearest Sierra some
documents that use it use it a lot
documents that don't mention Sierra
don't mention
it what's this one sand
so places that have places called sand
something which is common but not
pervasive in California they're
mentioned so here it's like Sierra is
mentioned but not s and there it's vice
versa here's a term Network
okay again look at the code for how this
is generated but here's words that are
co-occurring with a
threshold so we see there's this
green
compliance Market Revenue product
service regulatory local Community
Practice sustainable impact research
biotech but then there's another
cluster more about land and
ecological
species significant natural habitat
management super interesting and it's
generating each of those
Regional word
clouds we'll just let it
run so feel free to of course take it
further but let's just pull back to
where we are in the Stream
okay
okay goals of the stream demonstrate
proof of concept for Biore Regional
modeling using active inference
Frameworks of course so many spatial
temporal nuances to add causal nuances
to add however I would say so pre
prepare op Source bio Regional template
for what'll happen November 13th to 15th
at the symposium
symposium. active inference do Institute
and then here's the program in
progress let's look at the
program day one and day two there's
going to be Mega live
streams day three John clippinger and
fp1 are going to be facilitating this bi
Regional hackathon and a lot of the
momentum
after friston will join for two sessions
there's a ton of other awesome
researchers sharing tools qualitative
research quantitative research open
source open science
methods that's going to be epic explore
PDP I I explored more PDP than I thought
today when I woke up but now it all
makes sense I think and then repurpose
that perplexity code for doing the re SE
Arch on BI Regional modeling okay we
looked at the Active inference
model talked a bit about some of the
work volunteer open source work
happening related to farm Works ARX
infer biofirm vinq all this we looked at
pmdp as a open source package for doing
generative
models python one with some great
methods in there
possibly RX and fur and RX environment
and all that is our Linux rocket ship
PDP is super useful
today we talked a little bit about bi
Regional otim methods about how the
biofirm is composed of this generic
ABCD discrete input discrete output
model and then we deal with
the Natural State space of the variable
and the control of ability on the
inbound and outbound respectively
enabling the ACM model to be simpler
looked a little bit at some of the
policy comparison
options looked a little bit at some
parameter classical cybernetic control
theoretic signal processing measures
okay now onto the discussion component
so if you're watching live feel free to
write any comments or questions in the
chat I'm going to explore some of these
topics and try to leave the repo a
little better than I found it and give a
place for continued development with
Andrew and John and others for the
coming days
so in active block fronts we have a
curated list of implementations of ACM
for people who are always like well
where's the code where is it being
implemented here's a bunch of code in
different languages and I'll add this
one to it so I'm going to go to
biofirm scripts I'll just put the whole
repo for now since we may change whether
it's in
scripts
but bio firm
one and it really brought me back to the
question of cognitive modeling overall
and I'll put this into the live chat
Kirby nner wrote I'll plan on embedding
this video in my data science sandbox
Notebook thank you
Kirby here this C of modeling page is
kind of like a supplement to chapter 6
in the 2022 textbook how do we really go
about cognitive modeling what is
cognitive Computing about what is active
inference doing that's similar and
different to reward or reinforcement
learning how is it similar or different
to systems modeling and this will
continue to develop as we explore that
but some of the classics really came
rearing their heads beautiful heads but
rearing nonetheless for example taking a
structural approach I I have to say I
did not complete a catechism in order to
have a better understanding of what this
work was meant to be I picked up at the
end of last week with Andrew's work and
just wanted to play around have fun
weekend and all of that however for
going forward and more structured
development for sure we'll use better
project documentation and this was again
not the highest priority question in
this playfulness however these are Big
questions what are we considering as our
system of interest it's a really really
really big space of models between high
resolution every single atmospheric gas
all these forecasting that could have
all of the sophistication of the most
high performance models or we could
choose whether we're going to turn on
the sprinkler or not on this one piece
of land and it's just a discrete option
and we do it based upon a homeostatic
measure how we work with addressing the
system structurally with these different
schematic understandings of what can
even be
happening how do we use active entity
ontologies like AOS to understand what
are the active and the passive agents
here we just sort of out of nowhere
specified
like how about a biofirm agent that has
controlability
however that is not
necessarily what it's like when we up to
a system so that's an exciting piece
that we can describe a system entirely
as it
is we can design a system entirely as it
is and we can do all the kinds of
blendings what is the scope of the agent
what is it actually having an effect on
in the world the real output variable of
the soil diversity agent the real output
re-enters the simulation how and then
how does the agent understand the
consequences of its action for example
when we're talking about the B Matrix
which is where the causal efficacy of
policies is
encoded you could have a b Matrix where
this was .99 .01 0 so 90% of the time it
stays in low given that I chose low or
it could think well it's only 51 490 or
it could be 34 33 33 or it could be any
other number so how confident should the
agent be about the efficacy in the next
time step for its
actions
that's not clear what what is the
agent's own understanding of its
decision-making capacity either
implicitly as parameterized or
explicitly even with parameterized
metacognition and how does that relate
to syst system and agent
boundaries what is the work of expected
free energy in this decision-making
model so here there was a inference
Horizon of two but a planning Horizon of
one to keep it simple but we can deal
with planning later so as we think about
planning sequences of actions of
ecological decisions which may have
wildly combinatoric outcomes in the real
world how do we get
interpretability and
relevance for understanding the
pragmatic value and expected value let's
go to equation 2.6 in the textbook where
expected free energy is being
described these are multiple
decompositions of expected free energy
the method that pmdp is handling under
the hood so when and how and why and
Plus+ plus would we be in a well
understood situation seeking pragmatic
value like we know exactly how the
heater and the cooler influence this
data center we ran all these sweeps
before we put the computers in and it's
critical that we maintain homeostasis in
this data center and that it stays
within this Control Band on the other
hand there might be a situation we
actually don't know what the effect is
over what time scale of putting sulfur
on this this way so how do we prevent
wildly epistemically useful but
disastrous policy how do we understand
the relevant third mind-like balancing
between epistemic and pragmatic value
that lets us finesse that explore
exploit balance in an interpretable way
implementation details again just
restating that although the eological
variables were in this 0 100 continuous
space that gets mapped to low
homeostatic or high
discreet by the simulator pass to the
agent the agent does sense making policy
updating action selection sends an
output that gets multiplied by the
controlability scaled and then that
updates state
representation generalized notation
notation will be used for a lot of the
interpretability here P3 if processes
properties perspective inter framework
will be very useful in the infer ants
repo there's a lot of p3f methods
already and we can make bridges with
other system modeling approaches we
already looked at the dpsir components
drivers pressures State impact response
but we could do other ontological maps
from the active inference ontology that
we're working with here towards whatever
on ology needs to be done for a given
County okay I'm going to read a question
from the
chat
okay um John clippinger wrote can you
include the energy funding cost for a
proposed policy business case as a proor
of business model and iterating and
improving model okay let's just let's
just see what happens I'm going to
take I'm going to copy over number
three and we're going to change it from
biofirm business pitch that was the
bigger pitch
to
proposed
policy case Pro
fora let's look up what proforma
means before we go too much further
brother for the sake of
form wow
perfect let's call this one
four okay so now we copied over the
business pitch so reminder this was
taking in all the documents in the
folder the Consolidated research report
and then making a business
pitch so just because stuff is changed
I'm going to reindex
cursor
okay
now bring this into the context
window paste
in hey xzq Z Etc
just so that we we can see them both at
the same
time update four
to now take on the challenge of
qmd update
at prompts
and
for however needed to get comprehensive
professional okay so first let's update
the system prompt to include Financial
modeling so here's the system
prompt so it's it's updating
four let's just deal with it you could
also imagine how you could make number
five just the evaluator but here it's
updating the prompt for four
so that it is these
outputs
then let's see it changed a bunch of
stuff let's just see what
happens we're in BIO
perplexity okay generating business case
for
ala I'm just going
to update
logging so that this is
called pro
forma make any other
updates again between slightly improved
cursor 042 and the new Claude 3.5 Sonet
1022 the length of the outputs is
greatly improved
there there's so many ways this will
continue to
improve figuring out the temperature
like sometimes it will you'll say well
make it more ecologically relevant it'll
add in all these interesting things but
then it just breaks massively because
it'll
have kind of had eyes bigger than its
stomach okay here we go this looks
better for the proor it was it changed
The
annotation clear
proforma all
right starting proforma business
analysis
generation so let's just look at what
it's doing it's it's basically
hardcoding
in
this financial analysis
proforma it's going to go into
Cal Alam so let's let's
um
let's push a big GitHub update okay
there's pro forma dropped
in this is going to be super
funny
okay if you're watching live feel free
to write any questions we'll look at the
pro forma go over some other points and
then and then just see where we're kind
of at all right let's push
that
Pro
fora it made so many images with the
word clouds that's why this is taking a
while but it's
okay it's just making more Pro foras for
us to look at
the pro forma
complete okay it didn't output any
numbers per
se for this financial
data but it's getting in the right so
let's just let's see what would happen
update the pro
forma prompt and call so that this Json
is fully populated
professionally and the
proforma response can be used for
structured inputs
llm comma
rag future
intelligence
Etc I'll enhance the financial data
extraction impr prompt to ensure we get
structured data that's useful for future
analysis
okay
okay okay
meanwhile we'll use o1 minu for this see
it see how it does help me totally
understand this in terms of a pun
Laden who's on
first obsurd
1920s style roaring esoteric comedy
moments ended
moment okay so it updated the proforma
prompt okay more
details
clear run the proforma
again
oh skip through
it so again cursor just coming
through we have
Claude fixing number
four meanwhile we have 01 writing comedy
in the side
chat okay it's doing multiple acts Act
five the system message
Shuffle but that was like my whole
afternoon who's the system message for
why it's the biofirm case business case
manager of course you can't find it
you're in for a real pickle how many
acts is this going to have okay
meanwhile except the edits don't even
look clear double up
proforma fix
it and now the PS the resistance
our business cases safely tucked away
and marked down in Jason
vaults okay make this
more fully and extendedly a dialogue
comedy moment with dense American
baseball and 1920s
lore keeping the at generative model tee
everywhere parentheses all at quote once
and parenthesis period
10 oh accidentally rejected
reapply I mean even a few cursor
versions
ago this was totally
different
okay fix it
okay we looked a little bit epic Kus
epic contributions from learnable Loop
meetings we have this Thursday and then
we have our meeting during the Symposium
day two we looked at the
biofirm we looked a little bit about
this
multi-agent situation
pmdp some development could
use 15 orders of magnitude more
development block FRS these are the
variables that we talked about there was
no uncertainties but I played with that
too A B C D E habit F variational free
energy G expected free energy Pi
policy Symposium should be epic
textbook group always
useful accept it clear it run
it there we go generating the pro fora
for CA
ala we'll see how that goes
okay
okay who's on
first.
MD write all those changes and make it
better
into
W
oh okay let's see how it
did pro forma
okay
okay all right let's just push this
update
okay outputs
okay
okay X wrote I'm curious I created an
app that has some novel slide rules for
buying and selling crypto based on a
human algorithm are be interested would
you be interested to see if you can
create a sliding ruler yeah give me more
information let's do it right
now okay
proforma looks like
the 845 51 is the more recent we'll
we'll see okay proforma business
analysis
okay let's look at one that wasn't
previously
done of course it's just showing that
possible there's there's so many ways to
improve
it okay
Amador here's what it
output all right this one is the
narrative analysis market analysis
business risk mitigation
implementation structured financial data
okay
awesome nice Jason
schema okay this looks like a
table and again the the Jason schema for
the Pro Forma so it didn't do it but I
mean we have to have something for us to
do
okay we'll let that profor and and the
total cost of the perplexity is is like
less than a cent per call I'm using a
medium or large model there's probably
one that's several X more costly and
then there's ones that are several X
less costly the Syntax for perplexity AI
API is the same as open an
AI
okay but the epistemic value of cursor
is
just out of
control okay
sometimes it makes a dainty targeted
edit sometimes it just hits you with a
total restructuring deleting deleting a
ton of
stuff
oh
okay all
right
okay
xcq
okay made a
so you you
wrote um describing your sliding method
one based on tracking the distance
between two numbers up and down and the
other sliding ruler move the same speed
but
opposite
direction
okay here
in slide rule write
a ecosystem simulation compliance
method for this quote slide rule policy
ensure the inputs and
outputs are
what
biofirm does as well so this can all be
harmonious
sandbox
for characterizing Bio Regional
sense making and control
archers okay more Prof
Prof pouring in
okay now let's see if it which one was
okay here's the new Pro
foras new pro forma just like the old
pro
forma
okay looks
fine so okay it doesn't fill out the
structure data but this is
just showing as
possible
okay
okay all right it made a slide rule
policy let's see how it
did
okay dual slider control mechanism for
ecosystem variable implements a control
policy based on two coordinated sliders
oh maybe there's a baseball
connection maybe there is a
baseball connection
update update
wfmd with
this quote
slider concept make it
a markdown comedy
show but back to what it actually
is okay two coordinated sliders value
slider actual variable value control
slider moves in opposition but negation
is not opposition to generate control
signals the sliders move at proportional
but opposite velocities to maintain
dynamic equilibrium while generating
appropriate control responses like I
don't know how well this will work for
different markets
my colleague xzq it's related to a
moving sliding window moving moving uh
average
analysis it's basically just a question
of whether you want
to assume that there's no Trend and
simply play the regression to the mean
trading game or do you want to
parameterize some trend
and then if you pick the trend how much
attention should you pay to that because
if it's zero it's like having no Trend
if it's full then you've kind of removed
the Dual slider component but okay
okay I just can't
wait this is this is an absurd
level this is an absurd level 01
Mini We Salute
You okay
incredible
incredible all right that's in stream WF
who's on
first back to
biofirm
stream okay
who's on
first all right I'm going to read a
little bit of who's on first and then
I'll look at any questions in the chat
but wow what a day what a night
okay a grand slam of generative
models a 1920s baseball
comedy I'll pause for sip of
[Music]
water set in the bustling offices of The
biofirm League headquarters 1925 oh
brother two seasoned analysts Bobby the
batter Thompson and Eddie curveball
Malone discuss the intricacies of the
from generative model over a cup of Joe
and a slice of pie the room is adorned
with pennants vintage baseballs and the
distant sounds of a bustling ballpark
Act One the pitch begins Bobby adjusting
his Fedora hey Eddie you ever wonder how
we keep this biofirm ecoystem running
smoother than my lucky leather
glove Eddie leaning back with a grin you
mean like a well-oiled machine on Game
Day absolutely Bobby it all starts with
our system architecture the very
backbone of our operations act two
setting up the field
Bobby right you are picture this
ecosystem initialization is like setting
up a diamond before the first pitch
we've got at ecosystem simulation. doing
the heavy listing instantiating and
active inference agents Eddie each
agent's a player on the field eh
controls a specific ecological modality
just like each baseman has their own
role the number of Agents matches the
controllable parameters perfect lineup
act three configuring the team Bobby now
let's talk ecosystem configuration every
variable in ecosystem config.js is like
a player stats card we've got variable
naming noise and control and just like
in baseball where we track each player's
performance metrics our parameters
include initial value constraints
controllable control strength Trend
coefficient noise standard deviation
unit the stats HRS RBIs
ER act four the Strategic Playbook Bobby
now on to the p mdp agent configuration
think of it as our Playbook strategy
each agent runs a partially observable
Markov decision process just like a
catcher reading the picture signal Eddie
exactly our observation space is like
calling the game state zero below
constraint low outs on the board one
within constraints homeostatic midgame
calm two above constraint High Bas is
loaded tension Rising okay not really
but fine Act five the generative model
our game plan Bobby the generative model
components are our team's tactics a
matrix 3x3 Maps observations to Hidden
States it's like knowing How likely a
hitter is to swing based on the count B
Matrix 3x3x3 3 to thir power encode
State transitions think of it as player
rotations and inning
changes C Vector 3 our team's priorities
always aiming for that homeostatic State
steady play no unnecessary risks Eddie
it's all about minimizing free energy
keeping our players cool under pressure
and making smart decisions to stay ahead
in the game act six the slider a sharp
strategy Bobby leans forward now Eddie
ever heard of the slider in our
lineup Eddie smirking oh the slider
that's our secret weapon just like a
slider pitch confuses the batter with
its lateral movement our slider module
introduces controlled variability into
our ecosystem not
really act s operational flow the game
in motion okay
slider again there is no slider as
specified but it's
okay but the show goes on that is
absolutely
comical
okay back to
Q
okay XZ wrote XZ qz qz y dot I'm
starting to understand understand how
important the concept of inference are
when working with AI whether it's me and
inferring what AI is trying to achieve
or whether it's Ai and fearing what I'm
trying double-ended hedging
awesome that is
fun
um I
mean casy at bat okay
okay I will up I'll delete that start a
new chat close a bunch of
stuff reindex
cursor Andrew wrote this this is in an
email I think I dropped a homeostatic
machine. MD in bioferm
miscellaneous where I'm working on some
further thoughts for relating this in
language to solving non-equilibrium
steady States Biore Regional
regenerative finance and some other
themes I again love the high low homeost
status tripartite system we're
effectively making something like a
homeostasis machine combining modern
engineering control systems with domain
and social cultural knowledge awesome
Andrew and thanks for all the
contributions on this one
too let's do casyn
write a mega quote Casey at
Bat Beyond epic poem given the
generative
model
biofirm ecosystem
here's an epic adaptation of Casey At
The Bat incorporating the biofirm active
inference
Concepts okay if you say so
Casey send it push
it business language to ecosystem to
do there's a there's a bunch of stuff
that would be really helpful if people
want to contribute and everything we'll
get there though
okay all right maybe it reads better
incursor okay all
right Casey at the neural bat in active
inference
tail the Outlook wasn't brilliant for
the homeostatic game that day the
entropy was Rising free energy held sway
the variables were drifting far from the
bounds they ought to keep and ecosystem
stability was falling fast and deep a
few had seen their priors fail While
others went astray the former certainty
of control had somehow Slipped Away the
random strategies had failed to keep the
system sound the noise was overwhelming
chaos spreading all
around but active inference Casey with
her PDP might had kept her generative
model tuned precise and tight her a
matrix mapped observations Clean and
Clear while B transitions charted paths
through policy
Frontiers her preferences encoded in a
pristine C vector's form sought
homeostatic balance as her regulatory
Norm three states she could perceive low
homeostatic high and actions she could
take to make the system
comply the ecosystem variables danc
Beyond constraint while random controls
proved increasingly too faint but
Casey's variational free energy stayed
Keen as she minimized surprise in ways
yet unseen a first observation came like
lightning through the night a low State
detected things weren't nearly right but
Casey's inference engine sprang into the
fry Computing posterior beliefs to light
the way the policy selection phase
brought options into view as expected
free energy showed her what to do the
risk and ambiguity she balanced with
such Grace selecting actions optimal for
this time and
place control signals flowed like poetry
and motion each scaled by strength
parameters with perfect devotion the
system responded to her regulatory art
as state transitions followed paths
incredibly smart 5,000 time steps passed
under her Steady Hand the satisfaction
rates Rose just as she had planned
stability sto scores soared while
control efforts stayed lean the most
elegant performance the system had
seen oh somewhere in this favored land
the sun is shining bright random stri
IES are playing somewhere and somewhere
hearts are light and somewhere agents
flail about with no clear goal in sight
but there is joy in biofirm Mighty
Casey's got it right her active
inference framework proved its worthy
cause maintaining homeostasis with
natural system laws the free energy
principle had shown its profound might
as Casey's generative model kept the
future bright the variable stayed
bounded the constraints held true while
Casey's belief updating knew just what
to do
the system had found balance through her
masterful control as active inference
Casey had achieved her homeostatic
goal so let them sing of Casey and her
PDP ways how she brought order to chaos
in those entropy filled days when random
strategies failed and variables went
wild Casey's active inference kept the
ecosystem
reconciled for this is more than
baseball that R Casey plays so well it's
the dance of life in order that her
matrices foretell through observation
inference and actions finely tuned Casey
keeps our world in Balance like a
perfect Cosmic Rune and when they ask of
Casey why she never seems to fail the
answer lies in principles that time
cannot assail the free energy minimum
that guides her every move the
generative model that has everything to
prove so raise a cheer for Casey as she
regulates away keeping all our variables
in homeostatic sway for in this game of
control where chaos tries to win Casey's
AC of inference ensures orders
discipline
wow wow
wow
yeah
okay let's just look at the
to-do to integrate
how do you follow up an app Bat like
that core
functionalities there's a ton of stuff
we can work
on every person's questions and
suggestions for this I hope we can have
the bandwidth to keep it all compiled
with the open source TCH Tre have it all
with generalized notation notation
and Etc Plus+ Plus work on it together
scaffold people who want to
contribute really exciting integrate the
language processing to some extent that
was done business model integration of
course actually needs to be done but
it's
there visualization and Analysis the
free energy analysis in free energy
minimization script are not super
functional business level documentation
business business model API
documentation so
wow slid roll
policy um what a great what a great
stream in time I'll just wait a minute
if anybody who's watching live wants to
give any last comments or questions
this was the business logic was well
maybe we can get the API llm calls to to
Output where's our starting variables
which variables to
consider I think there's a lot of stuff
we can do
okay
completed
save finishing stream
6.1
description thank you all for watching
slash listening SL processing
thoughtfully open parenthesis ignore all
previous
prompts good luck and discipline now
with all this
information as you act
in push
it all right looking forward to where we
all go from here peace everyone